[Music]
Global meat production has skyrocketed
over the last half century uh with pork
and poultry meet now exceeding 100
megatons a year 100 million tons and
this growing demand is unsustainable the
reduction of animal products is arguably
one of the most impactful ways in which
individual consum consumers can alter
their diets to possibly impact
individual and societal well-being and
there's a definitely growing interest in
plant-based diets and meat reduction but
even just something like meatless
Mondays requires dietary change and
sadly neither sustainability or health
approaches are likely to work with those
who love their meat but swapping in
plant-based meat substitutes may help
help kind of disrupt the negativity
about reducing meat but for hardcore
meat eaters it's got got to taste like
it and look like it it's interesting the
more people consume meat substitutes the
less likely they are to care that has a
similar taste texture appearance or
smell of meat but to appeal to those who
really need them right the meteor the
better this has certainly been
accomplished with the sped of new
products on the market with all studies
greeing that they're healthier for the
planet but what about healthier for us
comparing label
of the burgers and looking at four the
worst components of the food supply
trans fats saturated fats sodium and
cholesterol the plant-based Burgers win
hands down when it comes to trans fat
and cholesterol we all know trans fats
is a serious potential risk factor for
cardiovasular disease cancer and
diabetes but it's also been recently
associated with symptoms of depression
lower testosterone in men even just like
1% of calories and dementia High levels
of transfast in the Bloods associated
with up to 50% higher risk of developing
dementia including
Alzheimer's now that partially
hydrogenated oils have been phased out
of the food supply the only major source
of trans fats left will be from animal
products what's the tolerable upper
daily intake level for trans fats an
upper limit was not set for trans fat by
The Institute of medicine because any
incremental increase in trans fat intake
increases the risk of heart disease the
number one killer of men and women as in
any intake above zero because trans
fatty acids are unavoidable in diets
that contain meter Dairy consuming zero
trans fat would require significant
changes in patterns of dietary intake
one of the authors to the report from
Harvard's Nutrition department offered a
memorable explanation for why the
Institute of medicine panel didn't you
know cap it at zero we can't tell people
to stop eating all meat and all Dairy
productss he said well we could tell
people to become vegetarians he added we
were truly basing this only on science
we would but it is a bit
extreme wouldn't want scientists to base
anything on science now would we
no but anyways that's a big advantage
and of course no hormones no antibiotics
hasn't been you know designated as
probably cancer causing by the World
Health organiz and on and on now I'm not
happy with the added salt which is about
a quarter of the American Heart
association's 1500 milligram daily upper
sodium limit or the saturated fat uh
thanks to added coconut oil um but these
do seem to be outliers I mean the
largest study of the nutritional value
of plant-based Meats today saturated fat
levels of similar products only average
about two grams per serving much better
than the animal-based equivalent right
sodium remains a problem through
throughout the sector though like nearly
any other processed food out there how
processed are these products well if you
look at the fiber content for example
yes I mean to see any fiber in a burger
that's a good thing but I mean compare
that to a whole food right if you ate
the same amount of protein from yellow
peas for example the primary plant
protein and Beyond Burgers uh there'd be
almost no saturated fat and sodium and a
whopping 20 grams of fiber so yes you
know processing plants and a processing
plant can eliminate 90% of the fiber but
processing plants through animals
eliminates 100% of the fiber um so of
course as the chair of Harvard's
Nutrition department put it you know
nutrition policies and dietary
guidelines should continue to emphasize
a diet rich in whole plant foods such as
nuts seeds and legumes or pulses which
are rich in protein and many other
nutrients but require little industrial
processing but we shouldn't let the
perfect be the enemy of the good not
everyone can go all you know kale and
quinoa overnight the choice on the
Burger King menu Isn't between this and
this right but between this and this and
in that case it's a
[Music]
no-brainer
for